
### Deep Learning-Enabled Semantic Communication Systems With Task-Unaware Transmitter and Dynamic Data
2022 https://doi.org/10.1109/jsac.2022.3221991
IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications
Existing deep learning-enabled semantic communication systems often rely on shared background knowledge between the transmitter and receiver that includes empirical data and their associated semantic information. In practice, the semantic information is defined by the pragmatic task of the receiver and cannot be known to the transmitter. The actual observable data at the transmitter can also have non-identical distribution with the empirical data in the shared background knowledge library. To address these practical issues, this paper proposes a new neural network-based semantic communication system for image transmission, where the task is unaware at the transmitter and the data environment is dynamic. The system consists of two main parts, namely the semantic coding (SC) network and the data adaptation (DA) network. The SC network learns how to extract and transmit the semantic informa

### Joint Coding-Modulation for Digital Semantic Communications via Variational Autoencoder
2024 https://doi.org/10.1109/tcomm.2024.3386577
IEEE Transactions on Communications
Semantic communications have emerged as a new paradigm for improving communication efficiency by transmitting the semantic information of a source message that is most relevant to a desired task at the receiver. Most existing approaches typically utilize neural networks (NNs) to design end-to-end semantic communication systems, where NN-based semantic encoders output continuously distributed signals to be sent directly to the channel in an analog fashion. In this work, we propose a joint coding-modulation (JCM) framework for digital semantic communications by using variational autoencoder (VAE). Our approach learns the transition probability from source data to discrete constellation symbols, thereby avoiding the non-differentiability problem of digital modulation. Meanwhile, by jointly designing the coding and modulation process together, we can match the obtained modulation strategy wi

### CDDM: Channel Denoising Diffusion Models for Wireless Semantic Communications
2024 https://doi.org/10.1109/twc.2024.3379244
IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications
Diffusion models (DM) can gradually learn to remove noise, which have been widely used in artificial intelligence generated content (AIGC) in recent years. The property of DM for eliminating noise leads us to wonder whether DM can be applied to wireless communications to help the receiver mitigate the channel noise. To address this, we propose channel denoising diffusion models (CDDM) for semantic communications over wireless channels in this paper. CDDM can be applied as a new physical layer module after the channel equalization to learn the distribution of the channel input signal, and then utilizes this learned knowledge to remove the channel noise. We derive corresponding training and sampling algorithms of CDDM according to the forward diffusion process specially designed to adapt the channel models and theoretically prove that the well-trained CDDM can effectively reduce the condit

### Improving Learning-Based Semantic Coding Efficiency for Image Transmission via Shared Semantic-Aware Codebook
2024 https://doi.org/10.1109/tcomm.2024.3450877
IEEE Transactions on Communications
Semantic communications have emerged as a new communication paradigm that extracts and transmits meaningful information relevant to receiver tasks. The trendy semantic coding framework, namely, learning-based joint source-channel coding (JSCC), lies on data-driven principles, with its efficacy depending on the employed neural networks (NNs). This paper introduces a codebook-assisted semantic coding method to improve JSCC performance for image transmission. Notably, a well-constructed codebook is employed to map each source image into a codeword, which subsequently provides shared prior information to assist semantic coding with general NN architectures. The main novelty is two-fold. First, we propose a general semantic-aware codebook construction method based on weighted data-semantic distance. In the case where the semantic information is characterized by discrete labels, this method is

### Deep Learning-Based Superposition Coded Modulation for Hierarchical Semantic Communications Over Broadcast Channels
2024 https://doi.org/10.1109/tcomm.2024.3447870
IEEE Transactions on Communications
We consider multi-user semantic communications over broadcast channels. While most existing works consider that each receiver requires either the same or independent semantic information, this paper explores the scenario where the semantic information desired by different receivers is different but correlated. In particular, we investigate semantic communications over Gaussian broadcast channels where the transmitter has a common observable source but the receivers wish to recover hierarchical semantic information in adaptation to their channel conditions. Inspired by the capacity achieving property of superposition coding, we propose a deep learning-based superposition coded modulation (DeepSCM) scheme. Specifically, the hierarchical semantic information is first extracted and encoded into basic and enhanced feature vectors. A linear minimum mean square error (LMMSE) decorrelator is the

### Multi-User Semantic Fusion for Semantic Communications over Degraded Broadcast Channels
2024 https://doi.org/10.23919/jcc.fa.2023-0766.202410
China Communications
Degraded broadcast channels (DBC) are a typical multiuser communication scenario, Semantic communications over DBC still lack in-depth research. In this paper, we design a semantic communications approach based on multi-user semantic fusion for wireless image transmission over DBC. The transmitter extracts semantic features for two users separately and then effectively fuses them for broadcasting by leveraging semantic similarity. Unlike traditional allocation of time, power, or bandwidth, the semantic fusion scheme can dynamically control the weight of the semantic features of the two users to balance their performance. Considering the different channel state information (CSI) of both users over DBC, a DBC-Aware method is developed that embeds the CSI of both users into the joint source-channel coding encoder and fusion module to adapt to the channel. Experimental results show that the 

### SNR-EQ-JSCC: Joint Source-Channel Coding With SNR-Based Embedding and Query
2025 https://doi.org/10.1109/lwc.2025.3526962
IEEE Wireless Communications Letters
Coping with the impact of dynamic channels is a critical issue in joint source-channel coding (JSCC)-based semantic communication systems. In this paper, we propose a lightweight channel-adaptive semantic coding architecture called SNR-EQ-JSCC. It is built upon the generic Transformer model and achieves channel adaptation (CA) by Embedding the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) into the attention blocks and dynamically adjusting attention scores through channel-adaptive Queries. Meanwhile, penalty terms are introduced in the loss function to stabilize the training process. Considering that instantaneous SNR feedback may be imperfect, we propose an alternative method that uses only the average SNR, which requires no retraining of SNR-EQ-JSCC. Simulation results conducted on image transmission demonstrate that the proposed SNR-EQ-JSCC outperforms the state-of-the-art SwinJSCC in peak signal-to-no

### Fairness-Aware Joint Source-Channel Coding for Robust Task-Oriented Communication
2025 https://doi.org/10.1109/jsac.2025.3638730
IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications
Learning-based joint source-channel coding (JSCC) is widely used in task-oriented communication, which aims to extract and transmit only task-relevant information to improve communication efficiency. However, the learning-empowered algorithms in task-oriented communication may lead to information leakage on sensitive attributes and cause discrimination towards specific groups, resulting in fairness issues in social equity. Meanwhile, directly adopting fair representation learning techniques in the source encoder of communication systems poses significant challenges: First, the favorable fairness-utility tradeoff in the encoded feature representations would be deteriorated by channel noise and dynamic variations. Second, the inherent separation of source and channel design precludes the efficiency offered by JSCC for end-to-end transmission. To address these issues, we propose a task-orie

### BitSemCom: A Bit-Level Semantic Communication Framework with Learnable Probabilistic Mapping
2026 https://doi.org/10.1109/lcomm.2026.3706984
IEEE Communications Letters


### Semantic Communication Over MIMO Channels via Score-Based Reverse Mean Propagation
2026 https://doi.org/10.1109/twc.2026.3703886
IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications


### ProMSC-MIS: Prompt-Based Multimodal Semantic Communication for Multi-Spectral Image Segmentation
2025 https://doi.org/10.1109/ojcoms.2025.3636725
IEEE Open Journal of the Communications Society
Multimodal semantic communication has great potential to enhance downstream task performance by integrating complementary information across modalities. This paper introduces ProMSC-MIS, a novel Prompt-based Multimodal Semantic Communication framework for Multi-Spectral Image Segmentation. It enables efficient task-oriented transmission of spatially aligned RGB and thermal images over band-limited channels. Our framework has two main design novelties. First, by leveraging prompt learning and contrastive learning, unimodal semantic encoders are pre-trained to learn diverse and complementary semantic representations, where each modality serves as a cross-modal prompt for the other. Second, a semantic fusion module that combines cross-attention mechanism and squeeze-and-excitation (SE) networks is designed to effectively fuse cross-modal features. Experimental results demonstrate that ProMS

### Mixture of Semantics Transmission for Generative AI-Enabled Semantic Communication Systems
2025 https://doi.org/10.1109/lcomm.2025.3611002
IEEE Communications Letters
In this paper, we propose a mixture of semantics (MoS) transmission strategy for wireless semantic communication systems based on generative artificial intelligence (AI). At the transmitter, we divide an image into regions of interest (ROI) and reigons of non-interest (RONI) to extract their semantic information respectively. Semantic information of ROI can be allocated more bandwidth, while RONI can be represented in a compact form for transmission. At the receiver, a diffusion model reconstructs the full image using the received semantic information of ROI and RONI. Compared to existing generative AI-based methods, MoS enables more efficient use of channel resources by balancing visual fidelity and semantic relevance. Experimental results demonstrate that appropriate ROI-RONI allocation is critical. The MoS achieves notable performance gains in peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR) of ROI 
